A Guide to James Hunter Terrell, Letters from former slaves of Terrell settled in Liberia, 1857-1866
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Manuscripts
  - Tibby Scott and Mary Scott to Dr. James H. Minor and Elizabeth Minor January 19 1860, ALS, 2 p.
    Tibby sends respects to Joseph and William Terrell, Mr Thomas Estres's family, Liess Harris's family, and Julia Ann Haliaday and her servant. The "little town" is described as having improved with more immigrants. School and church, the pastor of which is from Richmond, are active institutions. She requests various household items be sent to her.In the note from Mary, she tells Elizabeth how glad she was to get her letter. She likes the country very much. The daily news is that none of the girls have been married yet and she is raising fowls and ducks.
  - Hugh Walker to Dr. James H. Minor January 20 1860, ALS, 1 p.
    Hugh Walker writes of the ulcers on Sally's, Mary Jane's, Becky's, and Taylor's feet. He is short of time, food, and cloths and implies that some money owed could be used now. His children send love to Aunt Rachel, Rhoda, Nelly, Mr. and Mrs. Howell Lewis, and to Dr. Minor himself.
  - Julia Harden to Dr. James H. Minor January 20 1860, ALS, 2 p.
    Julia Harden describes items she needs for her household: clothes for herself, her boys and girls, shoes, and bed ticking. She closes by sending respects to the Doctor and his family and to Aunt Rachel if she is still alive.
  - Maria Barrett to Dr. James H. Minor January 20 1860, ALS, 1 p.
    Enclosed in this letter are two notes from Maria Barrett. She wishes Dr. Minor well and asks him to send her nails, linen, drill for pantaloons, and tobacco, among other minor requested items. She suggests that there is some urgent need for the listed goods. Maria informs Dr. Minor that she and her family are in good health and even though Charles and Richard Barrett have had ulcers on their feet for nearly two years, they are doing much better. Maria laments that she has not found anyone to suit her since the passing of her husband. She closes the letter by informing Dr. Minor that Mary has had twins, one of whom has died.
  - J.H. Paxton to Dr. James H. Minor February 15 1860, ALS, 3 p.
    J. H. Paxton gives an extensive list of the types of cloth and yardage that have arrived, dividing his list by the families and individuals for whom the merchandise was intended; Maria Barrett, Judy Harden, Hugh Walker, Tibby Scott, Willy [unclear] Franklin, Richard Barrett and grandchild, the Coleman family, Adeline Southall, and Lucy Twine. Mr. Paxton is indebted to Dr. Minor for the shipped merchandise but reminds Dr. Minor that if an invoice is not included with a shipment of merchandise it is subject to opening by the Customs house. Mr. Paxton's letter concludes that the freight and duty bills have been produced to him for payment along with costs for transportation. He questions Dr. Minor concerning who should be responsible for these bills.
  - William Douglass to Dr. James H. Minor February 22 1861, ALS, 1 p.
    William Douglass acknowledges the receipt of a letter from Dr. James H. Minor. Douglass sends $50 to Minor and asks Minor to divide the money among his children equally. Douglass also requests his family and friends to write to him about his children.
  - William Douglass to Dr. James H. Minor August 15 1865, ALS, 4 p.
    Douglass informs Dr. Minor of his family's state of affairs and then wonders why it has been almost four years since Dr. Minor has written. Douglass admits he is over anxious about Minor's silence especially since the Civil War is now over. He explains that his farming of sugar cane is going very well but wishes he could enjoy this new country with his children who are still in Virginia. This separation, he explains, is one of the hardest afflictions to bear especially since he sent Dr. James Hall gold for the purchase of them and has never had a response. He states he is ready to receive his children since his house is now finished but he is impatient to know what has become of them.
  - William Douglass to Friend [probably Dr. James H. Minor] January 29 1866, ALS, 3 p.
    Douglass reports the profitable sale of 8000 pounds of sugar which he produced in 1865, stating that he is too busy to travel to America as he had planned. He begs for news about his friend and about his own children to whom he has sent money and letters, but from whom he has heard nothing since the Civil War. He mentions that he had heard from a friend that two of his children had died and that he is saddened to have had no information whatsoever about his daughter, Julia.